Guide to the Cornell University Board of Trustees records, 1865-2001.
Cornell University Board of Trustees records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell University Board of Trustees records, 1865-2001.
2-3-74
Cornell University. Board of Trustees.
96.4 Cubic Feet.; 14.4 Cubic Feet.
Minutes and work folders.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Minutes and work folders for Board of Trustees and Executive Committee meetings.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Minutes and work folders for Board of Trustees and Executive Committee meetings.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Cornell University--Administration.; Cornell University--Executive Committee--Board of Trustees.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Material older than 50 years old is restricted for 75 years from date of creation or by permission of the University Archivist. Material less than 50 years old from the date of creation is restricted to permission of the Secretary of the Corporation or the Associate Secretary of the Corporation.
Reproductions may be made from the unrestricted material, but may not be published without the permission of the Secretary of the Corporation or the Associate Secretary of the Corporation.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Board of Trustees
Subseries Ia. Working Files
Subseries Ib. Minutes
Series II. Executive Committee
Subseries IIb. Minutes
Subseries IIa. Working Files
Series III. General Administration Committee
Subseries IIIa. Working Files
Subseries IIIb. Minutes
Series IV. Council on the College of Veterinary Medicine
Subseries IVa. Working Files
Subseries IVb. Minutes
Series V. Medical College Council
Subseries Va. Working Files
Subseries Vb. Minutes
Series VI. Agricultural College Council and State College Council
Subseries VIa. Agricultural College Council
Subseries VIb. State College Council
Series VII. Committee on Buildings and Grounds
Subseries VIIa. Working Files
Subseries VIIb. Minutes
Series VIII. Finance and Budget Committees
Subseries VIIIa. Finance Committee
Subseries VIIIb. Budget Committee
Series IX. Minor Committees
Series X. Photographs
RELATED MATERIALS
Includes former collection #2-5-5.
For the published Proceedings of the Board of Trustees of Cornell University see Archives LD1341.A1.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Board of Trustees
  - Subseries Ia. Working Files
    Files include resolutions, budget information and treasurers reports, correspondence, graduate candidate recommendations, faculty appointments, land reports, and ballots
    - Ledger book labeled Cornell University Reports Volume 1, 1866 - 1868 (Box 103)
      Includes hand written copies of proceedings of trustee meetings of the New York State Agricultural College and letters of significance to the founding of the University. Proceedings of meetings, on September 20, 1864, January 12, 1865, letters and reports to the trustees of Cornell University 1866-1868 regarding the committee on buildings, the New York State legislature, land script, building funds, copy of resolution regarding Genesee College and payment from Ezra Cornell. Report of the committee on organization submitted for the committee by Andrew D. White, discussing the subjects to be taught and needed professors of various subjects, how to find and recruit professors to Cornell, salaries, discussion of campus collections, observatory, library, military education, religion, etc.. Report regarding proposed theological seminary at Cornell. Letter from James Peck regarding music education, July 29, 1868. Letter from Charles Folger regarding land script, July 30, 1868. Inside cover has a letter to librarian George Harris from a Mr. Wilson January 26, 1897, saying the volume is from E.C. Russell, the son of Cornell Vice President William C. Russell, giving him the volume. Harris notes he presented the volume to President Schurman February 8, 1897.
    - Working files, 1864 - 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes university budget breakdown, Ezra Cornell donation resolution, invitation, and trustee election
    - Working files, 1866-02-12 - 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Working files, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Includes report on a theological seminary, "Notes for a Plan of Organization of the Military Department"
    - Working files, 1868-02 - 1868-04 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes Anthon Library purchase
    - Working files, 1868-06 - 1868-07 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes recommendation letters, memorandum of Military Organization Provisioned, Ezra Cornell sale of land scrips, supplication for the Institution of a Chair of Poetry and Music
    - Working files, 1868-08 - 1868-11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes Binocular Telescope letter and instructions, college land scrips fund
    - Working files, 1869-01 - 1869-02 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Working files, 1869-03 - 1869-05 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes letter describing conditions of Cascadilla, signatures of Cascadilla Place stock holders
    - Working files, 1869-06 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Working files, 1869-07 - 1870-03 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes proposal for medical department, resignation of board member William Kelly
    - Working files, 1870-04 - 1870-09 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes professor resignations and letter on Brazil expedition
    - Working files, 1871-02 - 1871-06 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes letter on Brazil Expedition, library report
    - Working files, 1872-02 - 1872-11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes White's resolution on the establishment of Sage Women's College
    - Working files, 1872-05 - 1872-06 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes proposal of reorganization of the College of Chemistry and Physics
    - Working files, 1873 - 1874 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes meeting of the Commissioners of the Land Office, land purchases
    - Working files, 1875-06 - 1875-11 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes resolutions about Ezra Cornell's death and burial, Cornell water supply, memorial tablet for John Stanton Gould, railroad, and Woodward/Cornell suit
    - Working files, 1876-02 - 1876-07 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Includes Woodward/Cornell suit information, resolution that no married people can be admitted to the university without permission from the Executive Committee
    - Working files, 1877-05 - 1877-06 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Includes commencement program
    - Working files, 1877-06-20 - 1877-06-21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Includes resolution from the Alumni Association calling for increased salaries of the assistant professors, petition for the return of Professor Byerly, donation of shells for the museum
    - Working files, 1877-09 - 1877-10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Includes correspondence regarding Professor Morris's Barn
    - Working files, 1878-04 - 1878-11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Includes letter from Stewart Woodford, petition from students on behalf of Professor Morris, description of charges of incompetancy against Professor Morris
    - Working files, 1879-06 - 1879-12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Working files, 1880-03 - 1880-06 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Working files, 1881-03 - 1881-06 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Includes letter from William Russell, resolution from the student body and student petition against the resignation of Professor Russell, submission of grievances from the Alumni Association
    - Working files, 1881-08 - 1882-06 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes list of lectures on the "Age of Reform in England" at Cornell, copy of Assembly Act No 177, Medical Department plan of Organization, Communications of the NY Association of Cornell to the Board regarding alumni voting
    - Working files, 1882-08 - 1883-04 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Includes resolution for a memorial to Ezra Cornell, John McGraw, and Jennie McGraw Fiske; resolution to establish a medical department in New York City, printed copies of resolutions establishing a Museum Council and Library Council
    - Working files, 1883-06 - 1883-10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Includes resolutions of the New England Association of Cornell Alumni, resignation of Willard Fiske, and printed resolutions establishing fellowships, scholarships, and a loan fund
    - Working files, 1884-01 - 1884-05 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Includes resolutions regarding the granting of degrees to students who did not complete their course, B.G. Wilder appointment as curator of Natural History, resolution to appoint a matron for Sage College and to set aside endowment money for Sage Women Scholarships
    - Working files, 1884-06 - 1884-10 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Includes petition from Sibley students and printed circular, and Act to establish a Board of Pharmacy, letter from students about university advertisements with cyanotype photograph of the advertisements
    - Working files, 1884-10 - 1884-12 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Includes report on the erection of a monument to Ezra Cornell, apointment of Agnes Derkheim as Principal of Sage College, New Orleans Exhibition, alumni petition
    - Working files, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Includes report on the conditions of Sibley, Professor Jones' petition, and a printed copy of A.D. White's resignation, printed petition of Cornell female alumni against compulsory residence at Sage
    - Working files, 1870 - 1885 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Includes report of the plans for a University Library Building, working copy of an indenture
    - Working files, 1886-06 - 1886-12 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Includes land report, appropriations recommendations, printed petition from alumni against Honorable Degrees,
    - Working files, 1887-01 - 1887-06 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Includes letter from A.D. White offering his library of over 30,000 volumes, sympathies for death of Mrs. A.D. White, report of the Committee to Procure Plans for a Library Building
    - Working files, 1887-10 - 1887-12 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Includes heating report, proposed library building studies, proposed Law School report, report on State Scholarships, resolution that stone be used for buildings on the arts quad
    - Working files, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Working files, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Working files, 1890-01 - 1890-06 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Includes report on Rhetoric and English Philology chair, many petitions of students against the raise of tuition, printed proposal for testing machines at Sibley
    - Working files, 1890-10 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Includes memorandum regarding the reorganization of the Department of Philosophy, department reports, amendments proposed to the Statutes submitted to the Trustees, organization of the University Senate
    - Working files, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Includes resolution to improve road conditions, printed report on Sibley College, printed plan and alumni resolutions for self-government for Sage College, resignation letter from C.K. Adams and trustee resolutions
    - Working files, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Working files, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Includes resolution for campus railway, statements on and objections to having street cars on campus, campus railway specifications, petitions to have railway on campus
    - Working files, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Includes equipment need for the Department of Minerology and Petrography, information on the campus railway and danger of electric disturbances, act to establish a state veterinary college at Cornell
    - Working files, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Includes official printed report of RH Thurston, scholarship for undergraduate woman submitted by Anna Botsford Comstock and Mary Fowler
    - Working files, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Includes official printed report of RH Thurston, AD White letter requesting a continued lease on the President's House, Mr. Fairweather bequeathment, petition for route of Railway, AD White proposal for the building of Sage stone bridge and gate across Cascadilla
    - Working files, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Includes printed information about library circulars and withdrawals
    - Working files, 1902 - 1904 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Includes Guiteau student loan fund, death of Alonzo Cornell
    - Working files, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes information on the Carnegie Foundation, copy of library general rules, with corrections and annotations
    - Working files, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      Includes report of committee on University Playground and Athletic Field, transfer of the Medical College Laboratory in New York City to Cornell, donation of pensions by Carnegie Foundation, Chinese student scholarship, appeal for land lease for Sphinx Head Society
    - Rolled student petition against the campus railway, 1906 (Box 3)
      Approximately 36 feet long
    - Working files, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes withdrawal of Sphinx Head Society petition, suggestion for reestablishment of Cornell Forest School, Sage College report, Seal and Serpent land lease petition, Sphinx Head and Quill and Dagger land lease petition, memoranda regarding grill work in Barnes Hall
    - Working files, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
      Includes lab receipts, documents on water pressure for fire uses, Medical College Council meeting, report of the Committee on Improvement of Salaries
    - Working files, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes report on proposed department abolishment in Sibley College, Cornellian Council appointments
    - Working files, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
      Includes "Needs of the New York State Colleges at Cornell University", Sage College sprinkler report and diagram of piping, report on student drinking and misconduct in Ithaca, statement on death of Goldwin Smith, sale of Llenroc Estate, The Cornellian Council printed letter, Studie for Cornell on the location of buildings for the Agriculture College, and library fund memoranda
    - Working files, 1911-01 - 1911-06 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
      Includes letter regarding Liberty Hyde Bailey as Commissioner of Agriculture, Bailey's report on the College of Agriculture, proposal for a busness farm or farm management farm, report on location of Risley College, photograph and plans of proposed college of Civil Engineering, report and blue print showing lines of proposed conduit
    - Working files, 1911-10 - 1911-12 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Includes report on proposed dormitory land, report of fraternity houses and dorms, formation of the Agricultural College Council, report on reorganization of State Agricultural College
    - Working files, 1912-04- 1912-06 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Includes report of Goldwin Smith's Will, Cornellian Council budgets, library and Fiske money reports and resolutions, petition to appoint Lieut. Joseph Beacham Jr. as Commandant of the Military Department, inquiry on Sabbatic Leave for professors, printed report on Sibley College
    - Working files, 1912-11 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Includes letter to A.D. White on his birthday, report and synopsis of report of committee on commencement and reunion plans
    - Working files, 1913-01 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Includes information on faculty participation I nthe University Government, report of the Committee on Cost of Student Instruction and Tuition (with charts)
    - Working files, 1913-05 - 1913-06 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Includes retirement letter from Liberty Hyde Bailey and resolutions, medical college list of staff,
    - Working files, 1913-10 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Includes inspections of fraternities and dormitories, letter from Madame Pansy Hadji Mischef asking for Bulgarian student scholarships, letters from the Cornell Women's Club of New York asking for more courses for women's vocations with endorsements and responses
    - Working files, 1914-01 - 1914-06 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Working files, 1914-11 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Includes proposed statutes of Cornell, committee report on Cornell Women's Club petition recommending the appointment of a women as department chair, a pamphlet of rooms available in Ithaca
    - Working files, 1915-01 - 1915-06 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Includes resolution of the Women's Club petition, Mr. Boldt's Luncheon seating chart, Report on vocational training for women, Cornell Calendar showing holidays and faculty meetings with number of hours per term committed to classes, printed budget packet for the College of Agriculture
    - Working files, 1915-11 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Includes report of the fraternities and dormitories, report of the proposed employment bureau
    - Working files, 1916-01 - 1916-04 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Includes Mr. Boldt Luncheon seating chart, Memorandum of Faculty Participation in University Control, letter from New York Women's Club on Dean of Women at other universities
    - Working files, 1916-06 - 1916-11 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes letter from Kappa Alpha Theta asking to rent a house, letter from George Hamilton explaining the publication of an anti-war letter, resolution to appoint a Dean of Women, proposed revision of statutes, semi-centennial endowment fund, Ten Year Book resolutions and samples, Cornell Statutes of November 1916
    - Working files, 1917-04 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Includes War Department special orders, letter from Harriet Moody regarding Adviser of Women, by-laws of the Associate Alumni
    - Working files, 1917-06 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Includes resolution on the occasion of Georges Mauxion's death in battle, report on undergraduate scholarships, report of the faculty in regard to the office of adviser of women
    - Working files, 1917-11 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Working files, 1920-11 - 1921-01 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Includes letters regarding changing the name of Sibley College, report of the Committee on University Publications, resolutions of the Cornell Chinese Students' Club, petitions for the appointment of Dean Smith as president, report of the Committee on the Reorganization of the Engineering Colleges, floor plan of dairy building, extract from Professor Orth's departmental report, report of Semi-Centennial Endowment Committee,
    - Working files, 1921-02 - 1921-04 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Includes proposed amendments to Cornell statutes, minutes of the committee on the Selection of a President and the Reorganization of the University, extract of Alma Webster's will,
    - Working files, 1921-06 - 1921-10 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Includes letter of retirement from George Lincoln Burr
    - Working files, 1922-02 - 1922-04 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Working files, 1922-05 - 1922-11 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Includes petition for consent to assignment of lease to Psi Upsilon and minutes, report of housing
    - Working files, 1923-01 - 1923-04 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Includes pamphlet of Statutes and Bylaws, report of the Council of the Delta Chi Alumni Foundation
    - Working files, 1923-06 - 1923-12 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Working files, 1924 - 1924-11 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Working files, 1925-01 - 1925-05 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Includes rules and regulations from the Committee on Health, printed booklet of Cornell Statutes
    - Working files, 1925-06 - 1925-11 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Includes notes on death of Burt Green Wilder, housing inspection
    - Working files, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Working files, 1927-01 - 1927-06 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Includes agreement between Society of New York Hospital and Cornell
    - Working files, 1927-10 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Includes a copy of "Build Yourself into Cornell"
    - Working files, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
    - Working files, 1929-01 - 1929-04 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Working files, 1929-05 - 1929-06 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Includes request for funds for War records, prize competition publication,
    - Working files, 1929-10 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Working files, 1930-01 - 1930-02 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Includes minutes of the Board of Governors
    - Working files, 1930-04 - 1930-10 (Box 5, Folder 4-6)
    - Working files, 1931-01 - 1931-05 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Working files, 1931-06 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Includes report on the faculty on compulsory military training, resolution to create the Provost's position,
    - Working files, 1931-10 - 1931-11 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Includes printed booklet on housing for men, amendments to the University Statutes,
    - Working files, 1931-12 - 1932-02 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Working files, 1932-03 - 1932-09 (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
    - Working files, 1933-01 - 1933-04 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Includes report of the Faculty Conference Committee on Military Training
    - Working files, 1933-03 - 1933-11 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
    - Working files, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 4-6)
    - Working files, 1935 - 1935-02 (Box 10, Folder 7-10)
    - Working files, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 11-14)
    - Working files, 1937-01 - 1937-06 (Box 10, Folder 15-17)
    - Working files, 1937-10 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Includes memorandum regarding proper corporate name of Cornell University
    - Working files, 1938-01 - 1938-02 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Working files, 1938-03 - 1938-04 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Includes correspondence regarding Professor James Boyle's remarks about NYS Dairy farmers
    - Working files, 1938-05 - 1938-10 (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
    - Working files, 1938-12 - 1939-01 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Includes Control of Traffic, Trespassing, and Vending on the Property of Cornell
    - Working files, 1939-02 - 1939-04 (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
      Includes report on Physical Recreation and Athletics
    - Working files, 1939-05 - 1939-06 (Box 11, Folder 9-10)
    - Working files, 1939-09 - 1939-10 (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
      Includes report of the Arboretum Committee
    - Working files, 1940-01 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Working files, 1940-02 - 1940-04 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
      Includes minutes of Board on Student Health and Hygiene
    - Working files, 1940-05 - 1940-10 (Box 12, Folder 3-5)
    - Working files, 1940-12 - 1941-02 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Working files, 1941-03 - 1941-06 (Box 12, Folder 7-9)
    - Working files, 1941-07 - 1941-10 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      Includes report of the Committee on Law, resolutions on naval and defense leave of absence
    - Working files, 1942-01 - 1942-07 (Box 13, Folder 3-5)
    - Mail vote, 1942-08 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Working files, 1942-10 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      Includes brochure "Cornell Women in the War", report of the special committee appointed to consider changes in the Cornell diploma, memorandum between Cornell and US Department of Agriculture relative to invesitgations on foods for Civilian and army use
    - Working files, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 8-12)
    - Working files, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 13-16)
    - Working files, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 17-20)
    - Working files, 1946 (Box 17, Folder 1-5)
    - Working files, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 6-9)
    - Working files, 1948-01 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      Includes documentation (resume) for appointment of Vladimir Nabokov
    - Working files, 1948-02 - 1948-05 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Working files, 1948-06 - 1948-12 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
    - Working files, 1949-01 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Includes first report of the Greater Cornell Committee
    - Working files, 1949-02 - 1949-04 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Includes discussion and report about Robinson Airlines (and Ithaca East Hill Airport), Exercises at the Laying of the Cornerstone of Statler Hall
    - Working files, 1949-05 - 1949-12 (Box 18, Folder 6-9)
    - Working files, 1950 (Box 18, Folder 10-13)
    - Working files, 1951-01 (Box 18, Folder 14)
      Includes terms and recommendation of Deane Waldo Mallott as president
    - Working files, 1951-02 - 1951-04 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Includes excerpt of report by acting president on Philip Morrison
    - Working files, 1951-05 - 1951-06 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Includes records establishing the Cornell University Archives, proposal to establish School of Industrial Labor Relations